ILGWU David Dubinsky Foundation Records 5780/104
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU David Dubinsky Foundation Records
1949-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
David Dubinsky Foundation
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/104
8 cubic feet
8 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Records include correspondence with reports from organizations that had received grants, meeting agendas and minutes of the foundation's Board of Trustees, and summaries of successful applications. Also contains a manuscript that chronicles the work of the David Dubinsky Foundation.
5516185
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
T. Figurasin, April 13, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Shortly after ILGWU President David Dubinsky's retirement in 1966, the union's General Executive Board established the David Dubinsky Foundation. The foundation provided grants to organizations that worked on issues relating to labor, immigrants, and liberalism, as these were three of Dubinsky's and the ILGWU's outstanding interests. According to the foundation's statement of purpose, the David Dubinsky Foundation sought "to aid those whose undertakings that are regularly not included in the normal work of the Union," and found "preference in projects of an inventive and experimental character" (5780/104, box 2, folder 23). The foundation's Board of Trustees were George Meany (Chair), Shelley Appleton, Isador Lubin, E. Howard Molisani, John P. Roche, and Louis Stulberg, and Gus Tyler served as the foundation's administrator.
Over the course of its decade-long existence, the foundation provided grants to a variety of project, and grouped them thus: New Immigrant Projects, Hispanic Immigrant Projects, General Immigrant Aid Projects, Blacks as Facing Many of the Same Problems as Immigrants Projects, Women's Projects (Women as a Minority), Consumer Interest Projects (Consumers as a Minority), Helping Minorities Outside the U.S., Labor Projects, Labor Education Projects for Workers, Labor Studies, Scholarship Projects, Voter Registration Projects, History Projects as Reminders of Struggles of the Past, and Medical Projects (5780/104, box 2, folder 34). The organization made its last awards in 1976, and ended in 1977.
The records of the David Dubinsky Foundation document the routine business of receiving applications, board of trustees meetings to determine awardees, and related correspondence and reports. Included are materials relating to meetings of the foundation's board of trustees, such as invitations, agendas, correspondence, reminders, and news clippings. The foundation's records relating to organizations that received grants include proposals for programs, progress reports, related correspondence, and news clippings. In some instances, information about these organizations are synthesized in annual reports that detail the name of the organizations and projects funded that year and the amount awarded. Additionally, the foundation records include proposals for programs that were not ultimately funded, as well inquiries from potential applicants. Together, these records document the range of projects that the David Dubinsky Foundation did or did not fund. A summation and analysis of this range is provided in an unpublished manuscript ("David Dubinsky Foundation Book," Box 2, folder 34). The David Dubinsky Foundations provided grants to organizations with projects or programs addressing one of the following areas: labor, immigrants, or liberalism.
Scope and Contents
The records of the David Dubinsky Foundation document the routine business of receiving applications, board of trustees meetings to determine awardees, and related correspondence and reports.
Included are materials relating to meetings of the foundation's board of trustees, such as invitations, agendas, correspondence, reminders, and news clippings. The foundation's records relating to organizations that received grants include proposals for programs, progress reports, related correspondence, and news clippings. In some instances, information about these organizations are synthesized in annual reports that detail the name of the organizations and projects funded that year and the amount awarded. Additionally, the foundation records include proposals for programs that were not ultimately funded, as well inquiries from potential applicants. Together, these records document the range of projects that the David Dubinsky Foundation did or did not fund. A summation and analysis of this range is provided in an unpublished manuscript ("David Dubinsky Foundation Book," Box 2, folder 34).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. David Dubinsky Foundation
5516185
- David Dubinsky Foundation Awards, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  List of 1972 recipients including brief information on each one.
- David Dubinsky Foundation - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Board of Trustees Meeting. November 30, 1972, St. Moritz Hotel, New York City. List of 1972 awards and recipients, plus the purpose of each organization.
- David Dubinsky Foundation - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Agendas and calendars of meetings throughout 1972
- David Dubinsky Foundation - Minutes of the Sixth Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Copies of a recap of the November 30th, 1972 meeting in St. Moritz Hotel, New York City
- Frontlash, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Frontlash. A Report and Evaluation.
- Roosevelt University, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Thank you letter and folder containing pamphlets about the university.
- Summary of Recent Court Challenges to Exclusionary Land-use Practices, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  A report prepared by Richard F. Bellman and Alice Baker and sponsored by the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing in September 1972
- Thank you correspondence from award recipients, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  List of recipients along with thank you letters from the David Dubinsky Foundation award recipients.
- National Council of Negro Women, Incorporated, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeals to David Dubinsky Foundation
- New York City Police Foundation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation and correspondence.
- Jewish Minorities Research, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence check enclosure.
- Recipients and Rejections, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Collection of rejected applicants and follow-up letters for recipients.
- American Association of Junior Colleges, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence between the two organizations.
- Taxation with Representation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Newsletters, reports, and correspondence.
- National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Industrial Relations Research Institute - University of Wisconsin, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal and reports sent to the foundation and correspondence.
- Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Hudson Guild, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation and correspondence. A photo is included.
- Youth Committee for Peace and Democracy in the Middle East, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Georgetown University, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence.
- Edward Corsi Labor-Management Relations Institute - Pace College, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence and class list.
- Workers' Defense League, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence, receipt, and a schedule.
- Pace College, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Thank you letter and receipt.
- Aspira, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence and receipt.
- Alliance of Latin Art, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Correspondence and a folder containing photos, projects, and agendas of the alliance.
- Frontlash, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Jewish Minorities Research, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Student-Labor Institute, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Pamphlets and correspondence.
- Consumer Federation of America, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- American Council for Emigres in the Professions, Incorporated, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation, annual report, and correspondence.
- David Dubinsky Foundation - 1972 Requests and Non-recipients [Part 1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. List of requests, renewals, and organizations who did not receive awards. Also includes appeals and reports.
- David Dubinsky Foundation - 1972 Requests and Non-recipients [Part 2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and various reports from the organizations requesting awards.
- Coro Foundation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and newsletters.
- The League of Women Voters of the U.S., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Consumer Federation of America, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Rutgers University, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and program and event schedules.
- Midwest Department ILGWU, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Labor Liberal Arts Program. Industrial and Labor Relations. Cornell University, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and list of classes of the labor program.
- 1972 Rejects (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Sixth Meeting" from November 30th, 1972. Rejections.
- Workers Defense League, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence, reports, and WDL Newspaper.
- A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation and correspondence.
- National Council of Negro Women, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and a flyer and biography about the organization.
- League for Industrial Democracy, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and pamphlets.
- Labor Liberal Arts Program. Industrial and Labor Relations. Cornell University., 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and a report.
- Alliance of Latin Arts, Incorporated, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and photos.
- American Council for Emigres in the Professions, Incorporated, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and a report.
- University of Wisconsin, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and reports.
- Frontlash, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and an envelope containing pamphlets, newsletters, and various information.
- Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence, pamphlets, and envelopes.
- Sponsors for Educational Opportunity, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Youth Committee for Peace and Democracy, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence, "Crossroads" bulletins, and flyers.
- Medgar Evers Fund, Incorporated, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to foundation and correspondence.
- Taxation with Representation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence, compendiums, and reports on correct activities.
- Coro Foundation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and reports on activities.
- Citizens Research Foundation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- City College of the City University of New York, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, and background information regarding a proposed project.
- Council on Religion and International Affairs, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Corporate Consolation Program.
- Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, proposals, and PRLDEF's first annual report.
- Labor Relations course, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Tentative outline for a short course in labor relations for senior high school students.
- New America, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation.
- Women's Lobby, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Various items including a proposal, pamphlet, and report.
- WNET/TV Channel 13, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation, correspondence, proposal, and a newspaper clipping.
- Pace College, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence.
- Georgetown University, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Correspondence and annual report from the university.
- African Labor History, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Appeal to the foundation and proposed budget for an African-American Labor Center.
- 1974 Rejects (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Rejected organizations for the reason that their appeals were outside of the foundation's scope and purpose.
- Board of Trustees Meeting, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Schedules and calendars.
- 1973 Agenda (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Agenda for the December 17th Meeting.
- Letters to Recipients, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Outgoing correspondence.
- Award Rundown 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Part of a collection entitled "David Dubinsky Foundation Seventh Meeting" from 1973 - January 16, 1974. Lists of organizations, including their purposes and awards. Also included is a summary of the 1973 meeting, rejected organizations, and organizations asking for renewals.
- Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Florida State University. Harry Goldman, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Thank you correspondence about grant.
- Letters announcing the end of the David Dubinsky Foundation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Sent out to various organizations on July 7, 1977.
- Correspondence regarding the end of David Dubinsky Foundation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Includes reports, newspaper articles, and letters about the end of the foundation.
- Statement of Purpose and Bylaws of the David Dubinsky Foundation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Various copies of both documents. Found in a an accordion folder dated 1977.
- Annual Report 1975 - 76. Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  This report was sent to the David Dubinsky Foundation in 1977.
- Stationary (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Unused cover letters and envelopes with the David Dubinsky Foundation logo.
- Notes and information on various organizations., 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Notes, photographs, newspaper articles, reports, pamphlets, and correspondence regarding different matters.
- Education, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Includes a report called "Academic Know-how in Action" from the Council of Negro Women, Inc. and an envelope labelled "education" from the Center of Migration Studies.
- Council on Religion and International Affairs, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  A report by the Corporate Consultation Program.
- Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  January 15, 1975. Copies of a report listing the 1974 awards, purposes, actions, and total grants.
- Immigrants (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Report about immigrants with no title page or a date.
- Schedule of Awards, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Schedule of Awards, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  January 15, 1975. More copies of a report listing the 1974 awards, purposes, actions, and total grants.
- Schedule of Awards, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  January 15, 1975. More Copies of a report listing the 1974 awards, purposes, actions, and total grants.
- David Dubinsky Foundation Book (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Copies of drafts of a book about the foundation. Undated.
- ILGWU Education Department, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Correspondence regarding Teacher Report Forms. August 8, 1972.
- General Information on Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Copies of schedule of 1974 awards, correspondence, and agendas concerning the January 15, 1975 St. Moritz Hotel, New York City meeting.
- Correspondence to and from Gus Tyler, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Correspondence, agendas, and notes to Gus Tyler regarding Board of Trustees meetings and other union information. Also includes a newspaper with a David Dubinsky Foundation article.
- 1974 Awards. Agenda, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Agenda for January 15th Meeting.
- 1974 Awards. Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Correspondence, notes, reports, and agendas regarding the meeting.
- 1974 Awards. Recipients, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Lists and reports on grant recipients along with the intended purpose and how much was given.
- 1974 Awards. Rejections (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Rejection letters to various organizations through January.
- 1974 Awards. Letters (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Letters to various organizations regarding the grant amount that they would receive. Thank you responses are included.
- 1974 Awards. Mail Ballots, New Directions, and Jewish Daily Forward, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Correspondence between the foundation and these organizations.
- 1974 Awards. Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Various correspondence.
- 1974 Awards. Requests [Part 1 of 5], 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Appeals to the foundation, requests for grants, and correspondence. Includes various reports and proposals from a wide array of organizations.
- 1974 Awards. Requests [Part 2 of 5] (Box 3, Folder 9)